Preliminary Guide to the Karl Menger Papers, [ca. 1890]-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Karl Menger papers [ca. 1890]-2006
Menger, Karl
Extent: 29,500 Items 40.7 linear feet
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00888
Language: English and German.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Karl Menger Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1995.
Biographical Note
Mathematician and professor at Notre Dame University.
Collection Overview
Correspondence; notebooks; research and teaching notes; drafts of unpublished and published works; teaching materials; student theses; printed materials; and a few photographs. Mathematical subjects include curves theory, algebra, geometry, and the philosophy of mathematics. Many letters are from notable scientists; those written to Menger during World War II often comment on the hardships of colleagues still in Europe. Includes biographical materials relating to Karl Menger and to his father, the Austrian economist Carl Menger, and materials related to the history of the Vienna Circle (1920s-1930s), a group of scholars concerned with philosophy and science. Notebooks relate to Menger's early work as a student, and later notes on mathematical theory. Printed items include many European and American scientific reprints, textbooks, study manuals, and school publications.
Subject Headings
Menger, Karl, 1902-1985; Menger, Carl, 1840-1921; University of Notre Dame; Economists -- Austria Biography; Vienna circle -- History; Mathematics -- Study and teaching (Higher); Mathematics -- Philosophy; Algebra; Curves; Geometry; Economics -- History; Philosophy and science; Scientists -- Europe Correspondence; Mathematicians -- Austria; Mathematicians -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Europe -- Emigration and immigration; Germany -- History -- 1918-1933; Germany -- History -- 1933-1945
Contents of Collection
- Accession (1996-0004)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Writings and Speeches--Karl Menger (Box 3)
  - Writings and Speeches--Karl Menger; Writings and Speeches--Unidentified Authors and/or Fragments (Box 4)
  - Writings and Speeches--Unidentified Authors and/or Fragments (Box 5)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 6)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 7)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 8)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 9)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 10)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors (Box 11)
  - Writings and Speeches--Other Authors; Writings and Speeches--Drafts and Proofs (Box 12)
  - Writings and Speeches--Drafts and Proofs (Box 13)
  - Writings and Speeches--Drafts and Proofs (Box 14)
  - Writings and Speeches--Drafts and Proofs (Box 15)
  - Writings and Speeches--Drafts and Proofs (Box 16)
  - Research Notes (Box 17)
  - Research Notes (Box 18)
  - Notebooks (Box 19)
  - Notebooks (Box 20)
  - Notebooks; Clippings, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Conference Files, Printed Materials, Photographs, and Miscellaneous Items (Box 21)
  - Vienna Circle Materials (Box 22)
  - Teaching Materials (Box 23)
  - Reingold Papers (Box 24)
  - Oversize Materials (Box 25)
  - Oversize Materials (Box 26)
  - Oversize Materials (Large, Stapled and/or Pasted Drafts) (Box 27)
  - Oversize Materials (Large, Stapled and/or Pasted Drafts) (Box 28)
- Accession (2007-0127), 2006, 2 Audiocassettes
  The addition (2007-0127) (2 items; interfiled with addition 2007-0142; 2006) consists of 2 audiocassettes and a transcript of an interview with Abe Sklar, discussing Karl Menger, his colleague.
  This addition (2007-0127) has been interfiled into Accession (2007-0142), Box 33.
- Accession (2007-0142), 1921-1985, 5 Boxes
  The addition (2007-0142) (1000 items; 2.7 lin. ft.; 1921-1985) consists largely of reprints from Karl Menger and Carl Menger, organized chronologically. There are also copies of Karl Menger's calculus texts. Some of the material is in German. This is, allegedly, one of the most complete collections of Menger's writings available.
  - Calculus: A Modern Approach, 2nd edition, 1953 (Box 29)
  - 1921-1936 (Box 29)
  - 1937-1956 (Box 30)
  - 1957-1983 (Box 31)
  - Obituaries (Box 31)
  - Reviews, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Introductions (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
  - V-12 Notre Dame photocopies (Box 32)
  - Understanding Calculus, Part II, 1950 (Box 32)
  - The Concept of a Function, 1948 (Box 32)
  - Department of Math graduate degrees (Illinois Institute Tech.) (Box 32)
  - Calculus: A Modern Approach, 1952 (Box 32)
  - Understanding Calculus, Part I, 1950 (Box 32)
  - Educational Studies in Mathematics, vol. 4, no. 1, June 1971 (Box 32)
  - Introduction to Calculus, Part I, 1950 (Box 32)
  - Calculus the Elements: Introduction Into Pre-limit Calculus for Everyone, 1966 (Box 32)
  - Calculus the Elements: Introduction Into Pre-limit Calculus for Everyone, Chapter II, 1967 (Box 32)
  - Untersuchungen uber allgemeire Metrik, date unknown (Box 32)
  - Basic Concepts of Mathematics, 1957 (Box 32)
  - Galois Theory (by Emil Artin), 1942 (Box 32)
  - Algebra of Analysis, 1944 (Box 32)
  - Nomography ..., 1944 (Box 32)
  - Hahn: Die Krise der Anschauung, 1933 (Box 32)
  - Alte Probleme - Neue Losungen in den Exakten Wissenschaften, 1934 (Box 32)
  - Neuere Fortschritte in den Exakten Wissenschaften, 1936 (Box 32)
  - The New Logic, 1937 (Box 32)
  - Carl Mengers Erster Entwurf zu seinum Hauptwerk Grundsatze, 1963 (Box 33)
  - On the Principles of Statistical Interference (by Abraham Ward), 1952 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 1, 1939 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 2, 1940 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 3, 1941 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 4, date unknown (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 5-6, 1944 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 7, 1946 (Box 33)
  - Reports of a Mathematical Colloquium, Issue 8, 1948 (Box 33)
  - Accession (2007-0127): 2 audiocassettes and a transcript of an interview with Abe Sklar, 2006 (Box 33)